<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" 
      xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" 
      xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" 
      xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" 
      version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>Kurian Benoy</title>
<link>https://kurianbenoy.com/blog.html</link>
<atom:link href="https://kurianbenoy.com/blog.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
<description>Recent posts on kurianbenoy.com</description>
<generator>quarto-1.4.551</generator>
<lastBuildDate>Tue, 12 Mar 2024 00:00:00 GMT</lastBuildDate>
<item>
  <title>📢 Last Week in AI(LWAI) - March 4th to March 10th 📅🤖</title>
  <dc:creator>Kurian Benoy</dc:creator>
  <link>https://kurianbenoy.com/posts/2024/lwai_march_2nd_week.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>🗓️ Monday:</p>
<p>The Government of India’s Ministry of Electronics and Information Technology (MeiTY) made an announcement regarding the deployment of ML models in production. While it was initially interpreted as a requirement for all, they clarified that it applies mainly to large organizations and not startups or Indie Hackers. This topic is still in the early stages of discussion, and we can expect further regulation in the future.</p>
<p><a href="https://twitter.com/kurianbenoy2/status/1764308982569763078">Tweet Link:</a></p>
<p>🗓️ Tuesday:</p>
<p>The AI4Bharat team released IndicVoices, a dataset containing natural and spontaneous speech, including read, extempore, and conversational audio, contributed by 16,237 individuals. This dataset is a significant step towards advancing AI in the Indian context.</p>
<p><a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.01926">Paper Link:</a></p>
<p><a href="https://ai4bharat.iitm.ac.in/blog/indicvoices/">Blogpost Link:</a></p>
<p>🗓️ Wednesday:</p>
<p>1️⃣ Telugu LLM Labs introduced Indic Gemma 7B/2B Instruction tuned LLM model - Naverasa for 9 Indic languages. Developed by <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/ravidesetty/">Ravi Theja Desetty, a developer advocate at LlamaIndex</a>, this model is a game-changer for Indic language processing.</p>
<p><a href="https://huggingface.co/Telugu-LLM-Labs/Indic-gemma-7b-finetuned-sft-Navarasa">Models Link:</a></p>
<p><a href="https://github.com/TeluguLLMLabs/Indic-gemma-7b-Navarasa">Github Repo Link:</a></p>
<p><a href="https://ravidesetty.medium.com/introducing-indic-gemma-7b-2b-instruction-tuned-model-on-9-indian-languages-navarasa-86bc81b4a282">Blogpost Link:</a></p>
<p>2️⃣ Surya which is a document OCR toolkit that does accurate OCR in 90+ languages and Line-level text detection in any language came with awesome benchmarking results. They benchmarked against Google OCR and results looks really competitive which beats them even in few languages. More power to Open source.</p>
<p><a href="https://github.com/VikParuchuri/surya">Github Repo Link:</a></p>
<p><a href="https://twitter.com/VikParuchuri/status/1765440195124691339">Tweet Link:</a></p>
<p>🗓️ Thursday: Two Kerala-origin open-source developers, elopers, and Jithin James , hit a home run with their YC-funded company, ragas_io. Y Combinator announced that ragas_io is an open-source evaluation and testing infrastructure for LLM applications.</p>
<p><a href="https://twitter.com/ycombinator/status/1765497664240759133">Tweet Link:</a></p>
<p>🗓️ Friday: Answer.AI, a rising star in the startup scene, announced a collaboration with Tim Dettmers, Huggingface, and Mobius Labs. Together, they are releasing a groundbreaking project that enables efficient training of very large models (70b) on consumer gaming GPUs using FSDP/QLoRA.</p>
<p><a href="https://www.answer.ai/posts/2024-03-06-fsdp-qlora.html">Blog Link:</a></p>
<p>🗓️ Saturday:</p>
<p>1️⃣ Simon Wilson, renowned LLM expert and co-creator of Django framework, shared an insightful blog post confirming that the GPT-4 barrier has finally been broken.</p>
<p><a href="https://simonwillison.net/2024/Mar/8/gpt-4-barrier/">Blog Link:</a></p>
<p>2️⃣ Santhosh Thottingal delivered an intriguing talk on digital Malayalam typography. While not directly related to AI, font designing is a complex art that may be even more intricate than LLMs.</p>
<p><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ANiPlFCNDS8">Video Link:</a></p>
<p>That’s Kurian reporting about last week. Hope you enjoyed it. Let me know if I should continue doing this :P.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <guid>https://kurianbenoy.com/posts/2024/lwai_march_2nd_week.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 12 Mar 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Merging a PR after 7 years</title>
  <dc:creator>Kurian Benoy</dc:creator>
  <link>https://kurianbenoy.com/posts/2024/merging_pr.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<section id="my-first-commit" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="my-first-commit">My first commit</h2>
<p>I was trying to find my first git/github commit with this <a href="https://firstcommit.is">webapp</a>. You can also find what is your commit checking that website and <a href="https://firstpr.me/">first PR with this website</a>.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://kurianbenoy.com/posts/images/Screenshot_20240305_224512.png" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>My first git commit</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>This first commit was for my lab programs in C- Programming Language Labs during my BTech classes at Govt. Model Engineering College. You might have wondered why I might have pushed it in github? It was all thanks to my professor Bijumon sir, who recommended this way to get started working with git/github.</p>
</section>
<section id="after-7-years" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="after-7-years">After 7 years</h2>
<p>Today only I noticed a troll PR, send by my good friend <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/discover-jimmy/">Jimmy Jose</a> who is now a Senior Devops Engineer in Esper. He recently married and I went to attend the function. It was cool to notice he <a href="https://github.com/kurianbenoy/Lab-Cycle1-C-programming/pull/1">send a PR with comment wow</a> 7 years back. You should have reminded me early bro. I am all for trolls and merged it.</p>
<p>Thanks you Jimmy for your valuable contribution to my first github repository. It took some time to merge. Sorry bro.</p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>git</category>
  <category>coding</category>
  <guid>https://kurianbenoy.com/posts/2024/merging_pr.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 05 Mar 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://kurianbenoy.com/posts/images/Screenshot_20240305_224512.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="68" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Releasing MalWhisper models</title>
  <dc:creator>Kurian Benoy</dc:creator>
  <link>https://kurianbenoy.com/posts/2024/Malwhisper_v1/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>Released two version of fine-tuning OpenAI Whisper on medium and small checkpoint by fine-tuning on IMasc dataset. The models where released here:</p>
<ol type="1">
<li><a href="https://huggingface.co/kurianbenoy/Malwhisper-v1-medium">Malwhisper-v1-medium</a></li>
<li><a href="https://huggingface.co/kurianbenoy/Malwhisper-v1-small">Malwhisper-v1-small</a></li>
</ol>
<section id="about-imasc-dataset" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="about-imasc-dataset">About IMaSC dataset</h2>
<p>IMaSC is a Malayalam text and speech corpus made available by ICFOSS for the purpose of developing speech technology for Malayalam, particularly text-to-speech. The corpus contains 34,473 text-audio pairs of Malayalam sentences spoken by 8 speakers, totalling in approximately 50 hours of audio.</p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>Malayalam</category>
  <category>Audio</category>
  <category>Deep learning</category>
  <category>finetuning</category>
  <category>SMC</category>
  <guid>https://kurianbenoy.com/posts/2024/Malwhisper_v1/</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 17 Jan 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>OpenAI Whisper and it’s amazing power to do finetuning demonstrated on my Mother tongue</title>
  <dc:creator>Kurian Benoy</dc:creator>
  <link>https://kurianbenoy.com/posts/2023/pycon_india2023_talk/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<section id="links-to-talk" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="links-to-talk">Links to talk</h2>
<ul>
<li><p><a href="../../../talks/pyconindia-2023/pyconind.html">Slides</a></p></li>
<li><p>Scheduled Time: Sunday, October 1, 2023, 11:00 AM IST</p></li>
<li><p>Venue: JN Auditorium, Track 1</p></li>
<li><p>Location: Jawaharlal Nehru Technological University, Hyderabad, India.</p></li>
<li><p><a href="https://github.com/kurianbenoy/malayalam_asr_benchmarking">Malayalam ASR Benchmarking project</a></p></li>
<li><p><a href="https://huggingface.co/datasets/kurianbenoy/malayalam_common_voice_benchmarking">Results for Common Voice 11 benchmarking</a></p></li>
<li><p><a href="https://huggingface.co/datasets/kurianbenoy/malayalam_msc_benchmarking">Results for SMC MSC benchmarking</a></p></li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="talk-in-30-seconds" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="talk-in-30-seconds">Talk in 30 seconds</h2>
<p>I talked about what is OpenAI whisper and some of it’s amazing feature. I highlighted the importance of fine-tuning Whisper in low-resource language like Malayalam which is able to get almost 90% accuracy compared to -10% accuracy of OpenAI whisper model weights. The results where calculated with a new github project called <a href="https://github.com/kurianbenoy/malayalam_asr_benchmarking">malayalam_asr_benchmarking created by me</a>.</p>
</section>
<section id="pictures" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="pictures">Pictures</h2>
<p><img src="https://github.com/kurianbenoy/kurianbenoy-website/assets/24592806/1e7fbe8b-ce77-4126-b6cb-42d641d02261.png" class="img-fluid" alt="Kurian speaking in pycon India"> <img src="https://github.com/kurianbenoy/kurianbenoy-website/assets/24592806/10f2ce20-d6e2-414a-9031-1f8a60a903e9.png" class="img-fluid" alt="Full view of Kurian speaking with the large screen"></p>
</section>
<section id="tweets" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="tweets">Tweets</h2>
<p></p><div id="tweet-27681"></div><script>tweet={"url":"https:\/\/twitter.com\/pyconindia\/status\/1708369432903553187","author_name":"PyCon India","author_url":"https:\/\/twitter.com\/pyconindia","html":"\u003Cblockquote class=\"twitter-tweet\" align=\"center\"\u003E\u003Cp lang=\"en\" dir=\"ltr\"\u003EAn engaging talk that left us all spellbound at \u003Ca href=\"https:\/\/twitter.com\/hashtag\/PyConIndia2023?src=hash&amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw\"\u003E#PyConIndia2023\u003C\/a\u003E by our Speaker Kurian Benoy (\u003Ca href=\"https:\/\/twitter.com\/kurianbenoy2?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw\"\u003E@kurianbenoy2\u003C\/a\u003E) on &quot;OpenAI Whisper and it’s amazing power to do fine-tuning demonstrated in my mother-tongue&quot;. It was an exploration of the thrilling fusion of Python and innovation \uD83D\uDD25 \u003Ca href=\"https:\/\/t.co\/3deZLjJNiw\"\u003Epic.twitter.com\/3deZLjJNiw\u003C\/a\u003E\u003C\/p\u003E&mdash; PyCon India (@pyconindia) \u003Ca href=\"https:\/\/twitter.com\/pyconindia\/status\/1708369432903553187?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw\"\u003EOctober 1, 2023\u003C\/a\u003E\u003C\/blockquote\u003E\n\u003Cscript async src=\"https:\/\/platform.twitter.com\/widgets.js\" charset=\"utf-8\"\u003E\u003C\/script\u003E\n\n","width":550,"height":null,"type":"rich","cache_age":"3153600000","provider_name":"Twitter","provider_url":"https:\/\/twitter.com","version":"1.0"};document.getElementById("tweet-27681").innerHTML = tweet["html"];</script><p></p>
<p></p><div id="tweet-46221"></div><script>tweet={"url":"https:\/\/twitter.com\/pyconindia\/status\/1714265134917702040","author_name":"PyCon India","author_url":"https:\/\/twitter.com\/pyconindia","html":"\u003Cblockquote class=\"twitter-tweet\" align=\"center\"\u003E\u003Cp lang=\"en\" dir=\"ltr\"\u003EA massive thank you to all the brilliant speakers of \u003Ca href=\"https:\/\/twitter.com\/hashtag\/PyConIndia2023?src=hash&amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw\"\u003E#PyConIndia2023\u003C\/a\u003E! \uD83C\uDFA4 Your insights, knowledge and passion for Python has truly enriched our event \uD83D\uDE03\u003Ca href=\"https:\/\/twitter.com\/hashtag\/PyConIndia?src=hash&amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw\"\u003E#PyConIndia\u003C\/a\u003E \u003Ca href=\"https:\/\/twitter.com\/hashtag\/PythonForAll?src=hash&amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw\"\u003E#PythonForAll\u003C\/a\u003E \u003Ca href=\"https:\/\/twitter.com\/hashtag\/CodeCollaborateCelebrate?src=hash&amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw\"\u003E#CodeCollaborateCelebrate\u003C\/a\u003E \u003Ca href=\"https:\/\/t.co\/TZSMJBT6Kp\"\u003Epic.twitter.com\/TZSMJBT6Kp\u003C\/a\u003E\u003C\/p\u003E&mdash; PyCon India (@pyconindia) \u003Ca href=\"https:\/\/twitter.com\/pyconindia\/status\/1714265134917702040?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw\"\u003EOctober 17, 2023\u003C\/a\u003E\u003C\/blockquote\u003E\n\u003Cscript async src=\"https:\/\/platform.twitter.com\/widgets.js\" charset=\"utf-8\"\u003E\u003C\/script\u003E\n\n","width":550,"height":null,"type":"rich","cache_age":"3153600000","provider_name":"Twitter","provider_url":"https:\/\/twitter.com","version":"1.0"};document.getElementById("tweet-46221").innerHTML = tweet["html"];</script><p></p>
<p></p><div id="tweet-29846"></div><script>tweet={"url":"https:\/\/twitter.com\/kavya_manohar\/status\/1633755478818959372","author_name":"Kavya Manohar (കാവ്യ)","author_url":"https:\/\/twitter.com\/kavya_manohar","html":"\u003Cblockquote class=\"twitter-tweet\" align=\"center\"\u003E\u003Cp lang=\"en\" dir=\"ltr\"\u003EThere has never been a benchmark for comparing Malayalam ASR models. Thank you \u003Ca href=\"https:\/\/twitter.com\/kurianbenoy2?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw\"\u003E@kurianbenoy2\u003C\/a\u003E \u003Ca href=\"https:\/\/t.co\/Ay84OGzxWn\"\u003Ehttps:\/\/t.co\/Ay84OGzxWn\u003C\/a\u003E\u003C\/p\u003E&mdash; Kavya Manohar (കാവ്യ) (@kavya_manohar) \u003Ca href=\"https:\/\/twitter.com\/kavya_manohar\/status\/1633755478818959372?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw\"\u003EMarch 9, 2023\u003C\/a\u003E\u003C\/blockquote\u003E\n\u003Cscript async src=\"https:\/\/platform.twitter.com\/widgets.js\" charset=\"utf-8\"\u003E\u003C\/script\u003E\n\n","width":550,"height":null,"type":"rich","cache_age":"3153600000","provider_name":"Twitter","provider_url":"https:\/\/twitter.com","version":"1.0"};document.getElementById("tweet-29846").innerHTML = tweet["html"];</script><p></p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>conference</category>
  <category>pycon</category>
  <category>Audio</category>
  <category>Deep learning</category>
  <category>SMC</category>
  <category>Talk Page</category>
  <category>Python</category>
  <guid>https://kurianbenoy.com/posts/2023/pycon_india2023_talk/</guid>
  <pubDate>Sun, 01 Oct 2023 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://kurianbenoy.com/posts/2023/pycon_india2023_talk/kurian_pycon_2023.jpeg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Chess is sometimes more entertaining than Cricket</title>
  <dc:creator>Kurian Benoy</dc:creator>
  <link>https://kurianbenoy.com/posts/2023/chess.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>Chess is occasionally more entertaining than cricket, and this notion was brought to light during the finals of the Global Chess League between Triveni Continental Kings and upGrad Mumbai Masters. As an Indian, this statement may seem controversial, but it is important to acknowledge that this is not always the case. Having witnessed the match between these two teams, I can confidently argue for the entertainment value of chess in certain instances.</p>
<div class="quarto-video ratio ratio-16x9"><iframe data-external="1" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/Ipz5yp3HzL4" title="" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen=""></iframe></div>
<p>While I personally struggle with playing chess and do not derive much enjoyment from it, I find watching chess matches and following the intriguing personalities in the chess world to be quite engaging. The particular match I am referring to was a team tournament with six players on each team, competing fiercely for their respective sides. The format involved the iconic board, two men’s boards, two women’s boards, and a prodigy board.</p>
<p>The tournament began with two rapid chess games, with each player having 15 minutes of time. In the first rapid game, Triveni Continental Kings emerged victorious while playing with the White pieces, but in the second rapid game, upGrad Mumbai Masters managed to win playing with the same color. Hence, the teams had to proceed into a blitz match with each player having only 5 minutes of time. Triveni Continental Kings played as White this time but unfortunately lost. Consequently, in a must-win game for Triveni Continental Kings playing as Black, they achieved the impossible under such pressure.</p>
<p>The tiebreaker resulted in a player-versus-player showdown, where three players from each team competed against one another. Surprisingly, all three matches ended in a draw, intensifying the level of suspense. The fate of the tournament ultimately rested on the final match between GM Jonas Bjerre from Denmark and GM Javokhir Sindarov. Remarkably, Sindarov had won all four of the matches played in the finals so far, adding an extra layer of excitement to this decisive game. The match concluded with Triveni Continental Kings emerging as the winners when Jonas defeated Sindarov with a checkmate, securing the victory for his team.</p>
<p>The tournament itself was well-organized, and as someone who has been following it for a few years, it was pleasing to witness its growing popularity. The event sponsors, Tech Mahindra, an Indian company, contributed to the grand prize of $500,000. This exemplifies the support of Indian companies like Tech Mahindra and Tata Steel who are increasingly involved in sponsoring major chess events. Moreover, India boasts talented prodigies like Gukesh, Arjun, Nihal, and Pragg, adding further excitement and intrigue to the world of chess.</p>
<p>In conclusion, while cricket holds a cherished place in the hearts of many, it is important to recognize that chess has its own unique and captivating qualities. The final match between Triveni Continental Kings and upGrad Mumbai Masters in the Global Chess League demonstrated the enthralling nature of the game. This particular encounter showcased the intense battles, strategic maneuvers, and moments of brilliance that chess has to offer. By expanding our perspective and appreciating the diverse aspects of sports and entertainment, we can fully embrace the thrilling world of chess alongside cricket.</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>Note: This article was generated based on author’s first draft with gpt-3.5-turbo-16k model.</p>
</blockquote>



 ]]></description>
  <category>chess</category>
  <category>Life</category>
  <guid>https://kurianbenoy.com/posts/2023/chess.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 04 Jul 2023 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://i3.ytimg.com/vi/Ipz5yp3HzL4/maxresdefault.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>OpenAI Whisper and it’s amazing power to do fine-tuning demonstrated on my mother-tongue</title>
  <dc:creator>Kurian Benoy</dc:creator>
  <link>https://kurianbenoy.com/posts/2023/fossunited/kochi.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<section id="links-to-talk" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="links-to-talk">Links to talk</h2>
<ul>
<li><p><a href="../../../talks/foss-united/kochi.html">Slides</a></p></li>
<li><p>Scheduled Time: Saturday, June 24, 2023, 11:15 AM IST - 11:45 PM IST</p></li>
<li><p><a href="https://www.youtube.com/live/B0_HKAbe3kk?feature=share&amp;t=5784">Youtube Live Video Stream link</a></p></li>
<li><p><a href="https://github.com/kurianbenoy/malayalam_asr_benchmarking">Malayalam ASR Benchmarking project</a></p></li>
<li><p><a href="https://huggingface.co/datasets/kurianbenoy/malayalam_common_voice_benchmarking">Results for Common Voice 11 benchmarking</a></p></li>
<li><p><a href="https://huggingface.co/datasets/kurianbenoy/malayalam_msc_benchmarking">Results for SMC MSC benchmarking</a></p></li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="questions-received" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="questions-received">Questions received</h2>
<ol type="1">
<li><p>Why do you think thennal’s whisper model performed so well?</p></li>
<li><p>How hard is to do the fine-tuning of whisper model in terms of effort?</p></li>
<li><p>How resources do you think is required to do LLM fine-tuning?</p></li>
<li><p>What do you think are some way’s to improve Malayalam speech to text models even further?</p></li>
</ol>
</section>
<section id="thanks-to" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="thanks-to">Thanks to</h2>
<p>The organizers of this meetup were fabulous. It was nice to interact with organizers like Mark, Richard, Riya, Subin, Devdutt etc. One of my friends Arun who was batch-mate at MEC took some nice photos of me speaking. It was a nice experience interacting with fellow speakers like Faiz Mohammed, Andrew Bastin and Maheshwaran. This meetup helped me to meet some new faces and reconnect with some familiar faces whom I knew since my college days. Overall attending the FOSS United Kochi Meetup was a great experience for me and felt the meetup is organized excellently.</p>
</section>
<section id="photos" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="photos">Photos</h2>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://kurianbenoy.com/talks/foss-united/Foss_united_poster.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>Poster Image of my talk</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://kurianbenoy.com/posts/2023/fossunited/father.jpeg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>My father dropped me off to the meetup</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://kurianbenoy.com/posts/2023/fossunited/IMG_20230624_114019385.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>Talk outline</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://kurianbenoy.com/posts/2023/fossunited/IMG_20230624_114127105.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>This talk is not generated :D</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p></p><div id="tweet-33393"></div><script>tweet={"url":"https:\/\/twitter.com\/FOSSUnitedKochi\/status\/1672490010770014208","author_name":"FOSS United Kochi","author_url":"https:\/\/twitter.com\/FOSSUnitedKochi","html":"\u003Cblockquote class=\"twitter-tweet\" align=\"center\"\u003E\u003Cp lang=\"en\" dir=\"ltr\"\u003EBack to the talks again with \u003Ca href=\"https:\/\/twitter.com\/kurianbenoy2?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw\"\u003E@kurianbenoy2\u003C\/a\u003E talking about fine-tuning OpenAI Whisper capabilities in his mother-tongue aka Malayalam \uD83E\uDD29 \u003Ca href=\"https:\/\/t.co\/m91FruuzqS\"\u003Epic.twitter.com\/m91FruuzqS\u003C\/a\u003E\u003C\/p\u003E&mdash; FOSS United Kochi (@FOSSUnitedKochi) \u003Ca href=\"https:\/\/twitter.com\/FOSSUnitedKochi\/status\/1672490010770014208?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw\"\u003EJune 24, 2023\u003C\/a\u003E\u003C\/blockquote\u003E\n\u003Cscript async src=\"https:\/\/platform.twitter.com\/widgets.js\" charset=\"utf-8\"\u003E\u003C\/script\u003E\n\n","width":550,"height":null,"type":"rich","cache_age":"3153600000","provider_name":"Twitter","provider_url":"https:\/\/twitter.com","version":"1.0"};document.getElementById("tweet-33393").innerHTML = tweet["html"];</script><p></p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>Malayalam</category>
  <category>Audio</category>
  <category>Talk Page</category>
  <category>SMC</category>
  <category>meetup</category>
  <guid>https://kurianbenoy.com/posts/2023/fossunited/kochi.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Sat, 24 Jun 2023 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>AI with Malayalam Computing!</title>
  <link>https://kurianbenoy.com/posts/2023/debutsav_talk/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<section id="links-to-talk" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="links-to-talk">Links to talk</h2>
<ul>
<li><p><a href="../../../talks/mec/debutsav.html">Slides</a></p></li>
<li><p>Scheduled Time: Saturday, June 17, 2023, 2:45 PM IST - 3:45 PM IST</p></li>
<li><p><a href="https://github.com/kurianbenoy/malayalam_asr_benchmarking">Malayalam ASR Benchmarking project Github Link</a></p></li>
<li><p><a href="https://huggingface.co/datasets/kurianbenoy/malayalam_common_voice_benchmarking">Results for Common Voice 11 benchmarking</a></p></li>
<li><p><a href="https://huggingface.co/datasets/kurianbenoy/malayalam_msc_benchmarking">Results for SMC MSC benchmarking</a></p></li>
<li><p><a href="https://huggingface.co/spaces/kurianbenoy/Pallakku">Pallakku a Malayalam speech to text demo</a></p></li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="questions-received" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="questions-received">Questions received</h2>
<ol type="1">
<li><p>Why is Malayalam more complex than other languages like Hindi, Marathi etc. While I understand the methodology of comparing type-to-token ratio (TTR), isn’t it possible that the dataset used for comparison may not include all the words of a particular language?</p></li>
<li><p>Do you think whether just a privileged few people can do Machine Learning?</p></li>
<li><p>What do you think about Mojo, will it help in reducing the problem of few privileged people doing ML?</p></li>
<li><p>How much resources is required to fine tune Whisper models?</p></li>
<li><p>How much did it cost for you to do benchmarking in Malayalam?</p></li>
<li><p>Does a biriyani meal for a family in Singapore costs $30? (Apologies for my previous incorrect statement during the talk, where I mentioned the cost of one biriyani in Singapore might be about $30. This analogy was made to compare the cost of benchmarking models for Malayalam.)</p></li>
<li><p>I absoluted loved <code>whisper.cpp</code> because it’s able to provide timestamps as well, is it possible to implement timestamps in Malayalam as well?</p></li>
<li><p>What are your thoughts on LLM finetuning?</p></li>
</ol>
</section>
<section id="quiz-questions" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="quiz-questions">Quiz Questions</h2>
<ol type="1">
<li><p>Name three Malayalam fonts? (Hint: SMC makes a lot of fonts)</p></li>
<li><p>Who developed the user friendly GNU/Linux distribution called Slynux during his high school? (Hint: He is an xMECian)</p></li>
<li><p>Which was the best performing malayalam ASR model according to <a href="https://github.com/kurianbenoy/malayalam_asr_benchmarking">malayalam_asr_benchmarking</a> results?</p></li>
<li><p>What is the name for debian versions 11 &amp; 12?</p></li>
</ol>
</section>
<section id="quiz-answers" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="quiz-answers">Quiz Answers</h2>
<ol type="1">
<li><p>There are a lot of Malayalam fonts. Check <a href="https://www.smc.org.in/fonts/">SMC fonts page for answers</a></p></li>
<li><p>Sarath Lakshman, do check his <a href="https://www.sarathlakshman.com/about/">website</a></p></li>
<li><p>Thennal D K’s <a href="https://huggingface.co/thennal/whisper-medium-ml">whisper-medium-ml model</a></p></li>
<li><p>“bullseye”(Debian 11) and “bookworm”(Debian 12). Fun fact, all the versions of Debian is named after characters <a href="https://wiki.debian.org/ToyStory">in movie Toy story</a>.</p></li>
</ol>
</section>
<section id="thanks-to" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="thanks-to">Thanks to</h2>
<p>All the folks who asked questions and made the session interactive, a big thank you from my side. As a speaker, it was the first time I was satisfied with myself for making the session interactive. My session demanded an interactive session as my slot was just after having a delicious lunch of biriyani. Also a special thanks to the volunteer who distributed the chocolotes to folks who answered my quiz questions. The organizers of event were fabulous, a special mention to names of people I remember at time of writing. Thank you Jithin, Karthik, Alaka, Theerthana, Aneeta who was always there to help. Also it was nice to meet FOSSMEC faculty in charge Sony mam.</p>
</section>
<section id="photos" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="photos">Photos</h2>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://kurianbenoy.com/posts/2023/debutsav_talk/debutsav.jpeg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>Pookalam created by FOSSMEC team</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://kurianbenoy.com/posts/2023/debutsav_talk/IMG_20230617_093828555.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>Photo with my Debian Developer friend Abhijit P A</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<div>

</div>
<div class="quarto-layout-panel" data-layout-ncol="2">
<div class="quarto-layout-row">
<div class="quarto-layout-cell" style="flex-basis: 50.0%;justify-content: flex-start;">
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://kurianbenoy.com/posts/2023/debutsav_talk/IMG_20230617_140338687.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>Speakers of the event</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</div>
<div class="quarto-layout-cell" style="flex-basis: 50.0%;justify-content: flex-start;">
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://kurianbenoy.com/posts/2023/debutsav_talk/IMG_20230617_155155985.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>Picture from 3rd floor of MEC</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://kurianbenoy.com/posts/2023/debutsav_talk/IMG-1935.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>Gifts received as a speaker</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://kurianbenoy.com/talks/mec/kurianbenoy-qrcode.png" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>QR code pointing to my website generated with https://qart.charlesfrye.com</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>Malayalam</category>
  <category>Audio</category>
  <category>Talk Page</category>
  <category>SMC</category>
  <category>Debian</category>
  <category>conference</category>
  <guid>https://kurianbenoy.com/posts/2023/debutsav_talk/</guid>
  <pubDate>Sat, 17 Jun 2023 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://kurianbenoy.com/posts/2023/debutsav_talk/debutsav.jpeg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>OpenAI Whisper’s amazing power to do fine-tuning demonstrated on Malayalam</title>
  <dc:creator>Kurian Benoy</dc:creator>
  <link>https://kurianbenoy.com/posts/2023/summit23_iiit/oral.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://kurianbenoy.com/posts/2023/summit23_iiit/op_image.jpg" class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center figure-img" height="600"></p>
</figure>
</div>
<section id="links" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="links">Links</h2>
<ul>
<li><a href="../../../talks/iiit-kottayam-summit/index.html">Slides</a></li>
<li>Scheduled Time: Saturday, June 10, 2023. 3:30 PM IST</li>
<li>Venue: Tapovan, Academic block, IIIT Kottayam.</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/kurianbenoy/malayalam_asr_benchmarking">Malayalam ASR Benchmarking project Github Link</a></li>
<li><a href="https://huggingface.co/datasets/kurianbenoy/malayalam_common_voice_benchmarking">Results for Common Voice 11 benchmarking</a></li>
<li><a href="https://huggingface.co/datasets/kurianbenoy/malayalam_msc_benchmarking">Results for SMC MSC benchmarking</a></li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="questions-received" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="questions-received">Questions received</h2>
<ol type="1">
<li>How can you improve the Malayalam ASR model further? What are techniques which you can do next?</li>
<li>How are metrics like WER and CER?</li>
<li>Can you explain how you calculated WER, CER, time taken and model parameter size for your code?</li>
</ol>
</section>
<section id="update-15th-june-2023" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="update-15th-june-2023">Update (15th June, 2023)</h2>
<p>Excited to share that I won 2nd place in Oral Presentation category and won a cash prize of Rs 750.</p>
</section>
<section id="thanks-to" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="thanks-to">Thanks to</h2>
<p>My MTech project guide <a href="https://www.iiitkottayam.ac.in/#!/faculty/manu">Dr Manu Madhavan</a> for his feedbacks for my Oral presentation slides. I had incorporated his suggestions to make things more clearer in oral presentation. Nihla who is doing her PHD encouraged me to participate in this Summit and gave me the contact of another PHD scholar named Akarsh who told me what is the format Oral Presentation.</p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>academic</category>
  <category>life</category>
  <category>conference</category>
  <category>Malayalam</category>
  <category>Audio</category>
  <category>Talk Page</category>
  <category>SMC</category>
  <guid>https://kurianbenoy.com/posts/2023/summit23_iiit/oral.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Sun, 11 Jun 2023 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Releasing Vegam Whisper Family of Models and demoing Malayalam Speech to Text</title>
  <dc:creator>Kurian Benoy</dc:creator>
  <link>https://kurianbenoy.com/posts/2023/summit23_iiit/demo.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<section id="links" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="links">Links</h2>
<ul>
<li><a href="../../../talks/iiit-kottayam-summit/demo.html">Slides</a></li>
<li>Scheduled Time: Saturday, June 10, 2023. 2:00 PM IST</li>
<li>Venue: AA 127, IIIT Kottayam.</li>
<li><a href="https://huggingface.co/spaces/kurianbenoy/Pallakku">Pallakku a Malayalam speech to text demo</a></li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="vegam-whisper-family-of-models" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="vegam-whisper-family-of-models">Vegam Whisper Family of Models</h2>
<p>Inspired by <a href="https://github.com/guillaumekln/faster-whisper">faster-whisper</a> which is a reimplementation of OpenAI’s Whisper model using CTranslate2 speeds upto 4 times faster than <code>openai/whisper</code> for the same accuracy while using less memory.</p>
<p>CTranslate2 supports various quantization formats and we have trained models for the following quantization formats:</p>
<ul>
<li>float16</li>
<li>int16</li>
<li>float8</li>
<li>int8_float8</li>
<li>No quantization</li>
</ul>
<p>For Malayalam, I used the best model in my benchmarking study ie <a href="https://huggingface.co/thennal/whisper-medium-ml">thennal/whisper-medium-ml</a> and converted into all possible quantization weights.</p>
<ol type="1">
<li><a href="https://huggingface.co/kurianbenoy/vegam-whisper-medium-ml">kurianbenoy/vegam-whisper-medium-ml</a></li>
<li><a href="https://huggingface.co/kurianbenoy/vegam-whisper-medium-ml-fp16">kurianbenoy/vegam-whisper-medium-ml-fp16</a></li>
<li><a href="https://huggingface.co/kurianbenoy/vegam-whisper-medium-ml-int16">kurianbenoy/vegam-whisper-medium-ml-int16</a></li>
<li><a href="https://huggingface.co/kurianbenoy/vegam-whisper-medium-ml-fp8">kurianbenoy/vegam-whisper-medium-ml-fp8</a></li>
<li><a href="https://huggingface.co/kurianbenoy/vegam-whisper-medium-ml-int8_float8">kurianbenoy/vegam-whisper-medium-ml-int8_float8</a></li>
</ol>
</section>
<section id="code-to-run-faster-whisper-code" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="code-to-run-faster-whisper-code">Code to run faster-whisper code</h2>
<p><img src="https://kurianbenoy.com/talks/iiit-kottayam-summit/faster-whisper.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
</section>
<section id="demo-video--1-and-its-associated-output" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="demo-video--1-and-its-associated-output">Demo Video -1 and it’s associated Output</h2>
<div class="quarto-video ratio ratio-16x9"><iframe data-external="1" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/zm1gU8hRHxA" title="" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen=""></iframe></div>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>Oru Thai Nadam sang by Venugopal and Sreya, Lyrics by Sugathakumari</p>
</blockquote>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://kurianbenoy.com/talks/iiit-kottayam-summit/25s_audio.png" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>Output of clip from Video 1</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</section>
<section id="demo-video--2-and-its-associated-output" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="demo-video--2-and-its-associated-output">Demo Video -2 and it’s associated Output</h2>
<div class="quarto-video ratio ratio-16x9"><iframe data-external="1" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/fZZFCOkWquY" title="" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen=""></iframe></div>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>Sang by Sithara Krishna Kumar, Lyrics by BK Hari Narayanan. This was a song created spontaneously at MBIFL 2023</p>
</blockquote>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://kurianbenoy.com/talks/iiit-kottayam-summit/10s_audio.png" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>Output of clip from Video 2</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</section>
<section id="pallakku" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="pallakku">Pallakku</h2>
<ul>
<li>Pallakku is a Malayalam speech to text demo leveraging the model-weights of whisper family of models. It might be the first huggingface 🤗 spaces for Malayalam speech to text.</li>
</ul>
<p>Two options to try it out:</p>
<ol type="1">
<li><a href="https://huggingface.co/spaces/kurianbenoy/Pallakku">🤗 spaces</a></li>
</ol>
<p><img src="https://kurianbenoy.com/talks/delft-fastai/pallakku.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>You can try it out in <a href="https://huggingface.co/spaces/kurianbenoy/Pallakku">the below link</a>.</p>
<ol start="2" type="1">
<li>GPU-based microservice (coming soon.)</li>
</ol>
</section>
<section id="what-is-behind-the-name-of-vegam-and-pallakku" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="what-is-behind-the-name-of-vegam-and-pallakku">What is behind the name of Vegam and Pallakku?</h2>
<ul>
<li>Vegam is a Malayalam word which means speed.</li>
<li>Pallakku is a Malayalam word which means a palanquin. It is a vehicle which is carried by people.</li>
</ul>
<p>As an author of these work, I just wanted to say the meaning of these words doesn’t really have anything to do with the package. Vegam might not be the fastest Malayalam ASR model and Pallakku is named not to refer to the old colonial times. I just named it for the sake of naming it.</p>
</section>
<section id="thanks-to" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="thanks-to">Thanks to</h2>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://twitter.com/santhoshtr/">Santhosh Thottingal</a> for his support and guidance. Santhosh told me about faster-whisper and the utility to convert the model weights to various quantization formats.</li>
<li>Organizers of IIIT Summit 23 for giving me an opportunity to present my work.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="how-was-the-expereince-presenting-demos" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="how-was-the-expereince-presenting-demos">How was the expereince presenting demos?</h2>
<p>Demo presentations are events where you can interact with people during the scheduled time. There was an evaluation panel with one of chief guests of the event <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/dr-t-ramalingeswara-rao-784a903a/">Dr.&nbsp;T Ramalingeswara Rao</a> from TCS and one of the professors.</p>
<p>These sessions brought a hacker kind of vibe back to me. I was really happy to receive lot of curious questions and smiles received from folks who came to visit my demo presentation. I set up the demo in such a way that there was a wireless microphone and I would play a few audio files. They used to rate the output of the model.</p>
<p>Some of my professors who taught me in previous semesters like <a href="https://www.iiitkottayam.ac.in/#!/faculty/keshab">Dr.&nbsp;Keshab Nath</a> visited to see my demo and gave me suggestions. It was a nice vibe to interact with a bunch of BTech students in their second semester from Andhra Pradhesh. Even though they were not able to understand Malayalam, they just hung around and asked me questions :D.</p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>academic</category>
  <category>life</category>
  <category>conference</category>
  <category>Malayalam</category>
  <category>Audio</category>
  <category>Talk Page</category>
  <category>SMC</category>
  <guid>https://kurianbenoy.com/posts/2023/summit23_iiit/demo.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Sun, 11 Jun 2023 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://kurianbenoy.com/talks/iiit-kottayam-summit/huggingface.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="46" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Learning how to install malayalam fonts</title>
  <dc:creator>Kurian Benoy</dc:creator>
  <link>https://kurianbenoy.com/posts/2023/malayalam_fonts/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>I was working on Malayalam Speech to text models and the malayalam letters where not getting rendered properly. I was a bit irritated by it and I asked my friend <a href="https://thottingal.in/">Santhosh Thottingal</a> why <code>?</code> comes this way.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://kurianbenoy.com/posts/2023/malayalam_fonts/malayalam_font2.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>Malayalam rendered in Nirmala font.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Santhosh told me basically malayalam letters take 3 bytes compared to 1 byte for latin and if the text is broken in the middle of those 3 byte clusters, you will get invalid character and will be displayed as <code>?</code>.</p>
<p>Then he told me I was using one of the worst Malayalam fonts ie Nirmala by Microsoft which is the reason why I am seeing lot of rendering mistakes.</p>
<p>So I stopped working on Mayalam ASR models and thought of studying how to install Malayalam fonts.</p>
<p>I found personally two ways to install fonts and I want to share that here. There maybe another thousand different ways to install fonts which won’t be covered in this blogpost.</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>Installing with Malayalam Fonts - firefox plugins</li>
</ol>
<ul>
<li>Install the <a href="https://addons.mozilla.org/en-US/firefox/addon/malayalam-fonts/">plugin</a></li>
<li>Choose the fonts you want to use by selecting it firefox.</li>
</ul>
<p><img src="https://kurianbenoy.com/posts/2023/malayalam_fonts/firefox_plugin.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
<ol start="2" type="1">
<li>Installing on Microsoft Windows</li>
</ol>
<p>I just asked ChatGPT and it gave me the following steps to install fonts by SMC in Windows.</p>
<pre><code>To download SMC (Swathanthra Malayalam Computing) fonts for your Windows operating system, follow these steps:

1. Visit the SMC website: Go to the SMC website at https://smc.org.in/fonts/
using your web browser.

2. Choose the font: Browse through the available fonts and select the one you
want to download. SMC offers a variety of fonts for different purposes.

3. Download the font: Click on the download link or button associated with the
selected font. The font file will be downloaded to your computer as a
compressed (ZIP) file.

4. Extract the font: Locate the downloaded ZIP file and extract its contents.
Right-click on the file and select "Extract All" or use a third-party compression
tool like WinRAR or 7-Zip to extract the font files.

5. Install the font: After extracting the font files, double-click on the font file
with the extension ".ttf" or ".otf." A preview of the font will appear, and a dialog
box will open. Click on the "Install" button to install the font on your Windows system.

6. Font installation completion: Once the font is installed, you can start using it
in various applications such as word processors, graphic design software, or
web browsers. The font will be available for selection in the font menu
of compatible applications.

By following these steps, you should be able to download and install SMC fonts on your Windows
operating system. Remember to respect font licensing terms and only use the fonts
for their intended purposes.</code></pre>
<p><img src="https://kurianbenoy.com/posts/2023/malayalam_fonts/malayalam_font3.jpg" class="img-fluid" alt="Malayalam rendered in Manjari font."> <img src="https://kurianbenoy.com/posts/2023/malayalam_fonts/malayalam_font1.jpg" class="img-fluid" alt="Malayalam rendered in Manjari font."></p>
<p>After all this I asked Santhosh whether I have installed Manjari font correctly and he said it’s correct. It’s not every day you get to ask the person who built that font whether I have installed the font correctly or not.</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>Note: For linux, all these fonts are preinstalled by default as it’s packaged as part of linux distros.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>I am glad to have friends like <a href="https://thottingal.in/">Santhosh Thottingal</a> to ask questions like this. Santhosh has written lot of popular fonts in Malayalam like <a href="https://smc.org.in/fonts/manjari">Manjari</a>, <a href="https://smc.org.in/fonts/gayathri">Gayathri</a> and with his latest font <a href="https://smc.org.in/fonts/nupuram">Nupuram</a> he has created almost 100+ fonts.</p>
<p>In my opinion SMC creates the best fonts in Malayalam and check their website section on <a href="https://smc.org.in/fonts">fonts to learn more</a>. If you are interested to learn more about Malayalam Computing I had previously written a <a href="../../../posts/2019/2019-07-30-Malayalam_computing.html">blogpost</a> which is just a highlight of talk given by Santhosh on this topic.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>Malayalam</category>
  <category>myself</category>
  <category>SMC</category>
  <category>TIL</category>
  <category>malayalamtextmodels</category>
  <guid>https://kurianbenoy.com/posts/2023/malayalam_fonts/</guid>
  <pubDate>Sun, 04 Jun 2023 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Tributes to my first python teacher- Dear Jumana mam!</title>
  <dc:creator>Kurian Benoy</dc:creator>
  <link>https://kurianbenoy.com/posts/2023/first_python_teacher/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>In 2016 when I joined my BTech. for Computer Science, I was someone who didn’t love programming and CS was only subject I didn’t get A1 in my class 12 boards. In my semester I was taught Python by a wonderful teacher. She taught in a beginner friendly way and encouraged anyone to ask doubts.</p>
<p>She told us programming was not something to by-heart and there are multiple way to solve the same problem. One year back I called my teacher and thanked her. By then I had spoken in Pycon India twice as an expert in machine learning and core-python and was able to pay my bills by coding in Python. She was really happy about me and even asked me to send even the videos of my talks.</p>
<p>My dear Jumana mam passed away today. I was really blessed to have such a wonderful teacher.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>Life</category>
  <category>Python</category>
  <category>academic</category>
  <category>experience</category>
  <guid>https://kurianbenoy.com/posts/2023/first_python_teacher/</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 29 May 2023 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Malayalam Projects I am working at the moment!</title>
  <dc:creator>Kurian Benoy</dc:creator>
  <link>https://kurianbenoy.com/posts/2023/delft-fastai-talk/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<section id="links-to-talk" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="links-to-talk">Links to talk</h2>
<ul>
<li><p><a href="../../../talks/delft-fastai/index.html">Slides</a></p></li>
<li><p>Scheduled Time: Sunday, May 28, 2023, 3:30 PM IST</p></li>
<li><p><a href="https://youtu.be/c69VyJ16Mx4">Youtube Link</a></p></li>
</ul>
<div class="quarto-video ratio ratio-16x9"><iframe data-external="1" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/c69VyJ16Mx4" title="" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen=""></iframe></div>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://forums.fast.ai/t/delft-study-group-talks-mojo-and-malayalam-benchmarking-low-resource-language/106126?u=kurianbenoy">fastai forums post</a></li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="talk-in-30-seconds" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="talk-in-30-seconds">Talk in 30 seconds</h2>
<p>I talked about Malayalam language and what makes it hard to work compared to other high resource languages like English. Then I highlighted some of the Malayalam models build during Whisper event and why I went ahead to benchmark these models. These models where benchmarked on two datasets mainly Common Voice and Malayalam Speech Corpus. I also shared more about the <a href="https://huggingface.co/models?other=vegam">Vegam Whisper model family</a> for making whisper models faster. Also I shared about Malayalam speech to text demo <a href="https://huggingface.co/spaces/kurianbenoy/Pallakku">Pallakku</a> which I am developing now with Vegam whisper weights.</p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>Malayalam</category>
  <category>SMC</category>
  <category>Talk Page</category>
  <category>meetup</category>
  <guid>https://kurianbenoy.com/posts/2023/delft-fastai-talk/</guid>
  <pubDate>Sun, 28 May 2023 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://i3.ytimg.com/vi/c69VyJ16Mx4/maxresdefault.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Visiting main campus of Indian Institute of Information Technology, Kottayam</title>
  <dc:creator>Kurian Benoy</dc:creator>
  <link>https://kurianbenoy.com/posts/2023/iiit_visit/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>I have been staying in Indian Institute of Information Technology (IIIT), Kottayam for the past three days in order to partake in my 4th semester M.Tech exams. I absolutely loved my stay in campus.</p>
<p>During my stay I had some interesting conversations with faculties, students who are doing PHD, UG and my fellow professional classmates who are pursuing MTech program. Some of these conversations were around latest advances of AI, AI hype etc.</p>
<p>The campus boasts excellent amenities. I am thankful to all the warm smiles and kindness received from everyone in campus specifically the ex-jawans who are working there.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-left">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://kurianbenoy.com/posts/2023/iiit_visit/morning.jpeg" class="img-fluid figure-img" width="300"></p>
<figcaption>Early morning selfie with mist in background</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-left">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://kurianbenoy.com/posts/2023/iiit_visit/campus.jpeg" class="img-fluid figure-img" width="800"></p>
<figcaption>Full campus view. <a href="https://www.iiitkottayam.ac.in/#!/home">credits</a></figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-left">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://kurianbenoy.com/posts/2023/iiit_visit/campus1.jpeg" class="img-fluid figure-img" width="500"></p>
<figcaption>Campus buildings being constructed</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-left">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://kurianbenoy.com/posts/2023/iiit_visit/classmates.jpeg" class="img-fluid figure-img" width="500"></p>
<figcaption>Class-mates attending tea party hosted by our class-rep</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-left">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://kurianbenoy.com/posts/2023/iiit_visit/tea.jpeg" class="img-fluid quarto-figure quarto-figure-left figure-img" width="500"></p>
</figure>
</div>



 ]]></description>
  <category>myself</category>
  <category>academic</category>
  <guid>https://kurianbenoy.com/posts/2023/iiit_visit/</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 08 May 2023 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://kurianbenoy.com/posts/2023/iiit_visit/campus.jpeg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>OpenAI Whisper and it’s amazing power to do finetuning</title>
  <dc:creator>Kurian Benoy</dc:creator>
  <link>https://kurianbenoy.com/posts/2023/fossasia2023talk/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<div class="quarto-video ratio ratio-16x9"><iframe data-external="1" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/g3ysWcvPX5A" title="" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen=""></iframe></div>
<section id="links-to-talk" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="links-to-talk">Links to talk</h2>
<ul>
<li><p><a href="../../../talks/fossasia2023.html">Slides</a></p></li>
<li><p>Scheduled Time: Saturday, April 15, 2023, 9:30 AM SGT</p></li>
<li><p><a href="https://youtu.be/g3ysWcvPX5A?si=Q5VQOon_SBq9IGBI">Talk Youtube link</a></p></li>
<li><p><a href="https://www.youtube.com/live/sGWiXzsLGtI">Youtube live video stream</a></p></li>
</ul>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>Please note mine was the first session of the day. I noticed there was a audio issue at the start of talk, so you can <a href="https://www.youtube.com/live/sGWiXzsLGtI?feature=share&amp;t=149">start listening from 2:30 minutes</a>.</p>
</blockquote>
<ul>
<li><p>Talk Page: <a href="https://eventyay.com/e/7cfe0771/session/8074">Session Details</a></p></li>
<li><p><a href="https://github.com/kurianbenoy/malayalam_asr_benchmarking">Malayalam ASR Benchmarking project</a></p></li>
<li><p><a href="https://huggingface.co/datasets/kurianbenoy/malayalam_common_voice_benchmarking">Results for Common Voice 11 benchmarking</a></p></li>
<li><p><a href="https://huggingface.co/datasets/kurianbenoy/malayalam_msc_benchmarking">Results for SMC MSC benchmarking</a></p></li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="talk-in-30-seconds" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="talk-in-30-seconds">Talk in 30 seconds</h2>
<p>I talked about what is OpenAI whisper and some of it’s amazing feature. I highlighted the importance of fine-tuning Whisper in low-resource language like Malayalam which is able to get almost 90% accuracy compared to -10% accuracy of OpenAI whisper model weights. The results where calculated with a new github project called <a href="https://github.com/kurianbenoy/malayalam_asr_benchmarking">malayalam_asr_benchmarking created by me</a>.</p>
</section>
<section id="thanks-to" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="thanks-to">Thanks to</h2>
<p>In my talk I mentioned <a href="https://kurianbenoy.com/talks/fossasia2023.html#/thanks-to">the following people and organizations</a>. Beyond that first of all, I would like to thank FOSSASIA team for giving me this opportunity to talk in FOSSASIA Summit 2023. I would like to thank <a href="https://abhijithpa.me/">Abhijit PA</a> for taking pictures of my talk and Thorsen for moderating my session. <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/karunakar-vanama-182702145/">Karuankar Vanama</a> pointed out a typo in a slide which was corrected. I got a lot of support after this talk when I posted in <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/posts/kurianbenoy_fossasia-activity-7052803823953739776-KmkL?utm_source=share&amp;utm_medium=member_desktop">LinkedIn</a> and <a href="https://twitter.com/kurianbenoy2/status/1647246814410682368">Twitter</a> and few folks reached out to me after this talk. I am really thankful to all of you.</p>
</section>
<section id="questions-received" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="questions-received">Questions received</h2>
<ol type="1">
<li>Someone was curious to know the relationship between Malayalam language and the Sanskrit language?</li>
</ol>
</section>
<section id="photos" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="photos">Photos</h2>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://kurianbenoy.com/posts/2023/fossasia2023talk/IMG_20230415_094452682_HDR.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>During the talk</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<div>

</div>
<div class="quarto-layout-panel" data-layout-ncol="2">
<div class="quarto-layout-row">
<div class="quarto-layout-cell" style="flex-basis: 50.0%;justify-content: flex-start;">
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://kurianbenoy.com/posts/2023/fossasia2023talk/IMG_20230415_092949649.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>Volunteers helping me with the talk</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</div>
<div class="quarto-layout-cell" style="flex-basis: 50.0%;justify-content: flex-start;">
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://kurianbenoy.com/posts/2023/fossasia2023talk/IMG_20230415_090740256_HDR.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>Last minute preparation before talk</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://kurianbenoy.com/posts/2023/fossasia2023talk/youtube_livestream.png" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>A snap from live stream session of my talk</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>conference</category>
  <category>fossasia</category>
  <category>Audio</category>
  <category>Deep learning</category>
  <category>SMC</category>
  <category>Talk Page</category>
  <guid>https://kurianbenoy.com/posts/2023/fossasia2023talk/</guid>
  <pubDate>Sat, 15 Apr 2023 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://kurianbenoy.com/posts/2023/fossasia2023talk/IMG_20230415_094452682_HDR.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Four super powers of Jeremy Howard</title>
  <dc:creator>Kurian Benoy</dc:creator>
  <link>https://kurianbenoy.com/posts/2023/jeremy_habits/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<section id="about-podcast-interview" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="about-podcast-interview">About Podcast interview</h2>
<p>I recently stumbled upon a podcast interview with Jeremy Howard hosted by one of my fast.ai friends Alex Strick van Linschoten, around 4 years back. I am a big fan of watching interview featuring Jeremy and some unique question were asked by the interviewer which I haven’t seen anyone asking.</p>
<p>I would defenitely recommend everyone to <a href="https://www.sourcesandmethods.com/podcast/2019/6/28/sources-and-methods-44-deep-learning-with-fastais-jeremy-howard">give a watch to the podcast interview</a>. In this interview, Jeremy shared four super powers which he learned over the years. I am going to briefly summarize them.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-left">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/53e7b388e4b0b09d128a62b1/1561718846748-5KLJ2OZF4ZFVQOG9UNU3/jh-head.jpg?format=500w" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>Jeremy Howard</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</section>
<section id="four-super-powers" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="four-super-powers">Four super powers</h2>
<ol type="1">
<li>Spaced Repetition and learning how to learn</li>
</ol>
<p>Alex was very curious about how Jeremy learned chinese and his approach to learning. Jeremy answered as following:</p>
<p>I started learning Chinese not because I had any interest in Chinese, but because I was such a bad language learner in highschool. I did six months of French, I got 28% and I quit. When I wanted to dig into machine learning, I thought one of the things that might be better to understand was human learning, so I used myself as a subject. A hopeless subject. If I can come up with a way that even I can learn a language, that would be great. And to make sure that was challenging enough, I tried to pick the hardest language I could. So according to according to CIA guidelines, Arabic and Chinese are the hardest languages for people to pick up. Then I spent three months studying learning theory, and language learning theory, and then software to help me with that process.</p>
<p>It turns out that even I can learn Chinese. After a year of this - by no means a full time thing, an hour or two a day - I went to China to a top language learning program and based on the results of my exam got placed with all these language PhDs, and I thought wow. Studying smart is important. It’s all about how you do it.</p>
<p>Spaced repetition is such an easy thing that anyone can do, for free, you can start using it.<a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=HwH7bJibmdM">Jeremy’s amazing Anki talk</a></p>
<p>If you’re not using Anki, you’re many orders of magnitude less likely to remember a piece of vocab. So you come away like I did, thinking you can’t learn a language. But once you learn vocab, the rest is really not that hard. Don’t try to learn grammar, just spend all your time reading.</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>Recently, Rachel Thomas wrote a blog post about <a href="https://rachel.fast.ai/posts/2023-02-21-anki/">How to remember anything</a>.</p>
</blockquote>
<ol start="2" type="1">
<li>Doing Regular exercises</li>
</ol>
<p>Ten years back Jeremy suffered a injury because of which he lost almost 6 months. After that he is doing regular yoga and exercises.</p>
<ol start="3" type="1">
<li>Note taking</li>
</ol>
<p>Lot of times Jeremy have seen whenever someone is discussing about a particular topic, or issue. Those who take the notes on the topic immediately are the one to follow up even later and perform much better. Exceptional people take a lot of notes. Less exceptional people assume they’re going to remember.</p>
<p>Taking notes in class is kind of a waste of time. I don’t really see the point of going to class most of the time honestly, it’s probably being videotaped</p>
<ol start="4" type="1">
<li>Tenacity</li>
</ol>
<p>People who are successful practitioners in deep learning are the ones who have highest level of tenacity. He has found lot of people stopping midway and people who are world-class practitioners are always tenatious.</p>
</section>
<section id="two-critical-skills-in-ai-era" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="two-critical-skills-in-ai-era">Two critical skills in AI era</h2>
<p>The two critical skills going forward is:</p>
<ul>
<li>One is knowing how to use machine learning.</li>
<li>And the other is knowing how to interact with it and care for human beings.</li>
</ul>
<p>Because the latter one can’t be replaced by AI. The former one will gradually replace everything. Back in the early days of the commercial internet, being an internet expert was extremely useful and you could have a job as an internet expert and be in a company of internet experts, and sell yourself as an internet expert company. Today, very few people do that, because on the whole the internet is what it is, and there’s a relatively few number of people who need such a level of expertise that they can go in and change the way your router operates and such. I think we’re going to see the same thing with AI.</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>Thanks to <a href="https://forums.fast.ai/u/strickvl/">Alex Strick van Linschoten</a> who posted it in fast.ai forums and for writing <a href="https://www.sourcesandmethods.com/podcast/2019/6/28/sources-and-methods-44-deep-learning-with-fastais-jeremy-howard">wonderful show notes</a>, some of which I have used in this post.</p>
</blockquote>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>fastai</category>
  <category>Life</category>
  <category>myself</category>
  <guid>https://kurianbenoy.com/posts/2023/jeremy_habits/</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 04 Apr 2023 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://kurianbenoy.com/posts/2023/jeremy_habits/jh-head.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>🐦Learning more about birds and bird calls with Merlin app</title>
  <dc:creator>Kurian Benoy</dc:creator>
  <link>https://kurianbenoy.com/posts/2023/BirdCLEF2023/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>I recently went for a bird watching adventure in <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Salim_Ali_Bird_Sanctuary">Salim Ali Bird Sanctuary</a>, Thattekad Kerala, India. During that time, my guide was very proficient in identifying birds by just hearing sounds. In Salim Ali bird sanctuary itself there are almost 300 species of land birds and another 100+ species of water birds.</p>
<p>I was genuinely curious, how they learned about all these birds and memorized all these. This is when my guide talked about the Merlin app, which can help in learning more about various species of bird.</p>
<div class="quarto-video ratio ratio-16x9"><iframe data-external="1" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/xmSUOLxyatY" title="" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen=""></iframe></div>
<p>Video Explaining functionality of Merlin</p>
<p>You can download it from <a href="https://apps.apple.com/us/app/merlin-bird-id-by-cornell-lab/id773457673">Apple App store</a> or <a href="https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=com.labs.merlinbirdid.app&amp;hl=en&amp;gl=US">Google Playstore</a> for your android phones. Learn more about Merlin app in this <a href="https://merlin.allaboutbirds.org/.">link</a></p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://www.googleapis.com/download/storage/v1/b/kaggle-forum-message-attachments/o/inbox%2F1310697%2Fc0fa9ac858406ddcc9f644fc53054642%2FWhatsApp%20Image%202023-03-20%20at%209.25.36%20AM.jpeg?generation=1679301145365560&amp;alt=media" class="img-fluid figure-img" width="500"></p>
<figcaption>A photo during my bird walking trek</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sri_Lanka_frogmouth">The below image is Ceylon Frogmouth which is a rare bird in my region</a></p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-left">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://www.googleapis.com/download/storage/v1/b/kaggle-forum-message-attachments/o/inbox%2F1310697%2F2e84ee1ef3b246d9bcee2cd5757f4a05%2FWhatsApp%20Image%202023-03-20%20at%209.25.45%20AM.jpeg?generation=1679301247043893&amp;alt=media" class="img-fluid figure-img" width="300"></p>
<figcaption>Ceylon Frogmouth</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Note: This article was originally published in <a href="https://www.kaggle.com/competitions/birdclef-2023/discussion/396029#2188836">Kaggle discussion here</a></p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>kaggle</category>
  <category>experience</category>
  <category>Travel</category>
  <guid>https://kurianbenoy.com/posts/2023/BirdCLEF2023/</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 20 Mar 2023 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Everything is about to be changed and launch of GPT-4</title>
  <dc:creator>Kurian Benoy</dc:creator>
  <link>https://kurianbenoy.com/posts/2023/gpt4/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>Update: April 20, 2023</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>I found this <a href="https://world.hey.com/dhh/how-to-continue-making-kerosene-lamps-on-the-eve-of-electricity-5a8b8e1a">brillant article</a> on not to be too afraid of latest AI advances by David Heinemeir Hanson who is the creator of Ruby on Rails and co-owner of Basecamp. I think it’s a must read for anyone who is a bit worried about latest changes as well as for anyone who is excited about the changes.</p>
</blockquote>
<section id="buzz-about-chatgpt" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="buzz-about-chatgpt">Buzz about ChatGPT</h2>
<p>There has been a lot of buzz about GPT and ChatGPT in specific. Tom Scott, a youtuber recently published a video on how he used ChatGPT to fix a problem in his email backup program. He said it’s beginning of something new like how internet had literally changed everything 20-30 years back.</p>
<div class="quarto-video ratio ratio-16x9"><iframe data-external="1" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/jPhJbKBuNnA" title="" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen=""></iframe></div>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>AI is the new electricity - Andrew NG</p>
</blockquote>
<p>When I was writing this article, I forget the syntax of how to embed youtube videos in quarto markdown. I solved this issue by asking this <a href="https://quarto-bot.onrender.com/">question to Quarto Help Bot</a> which was made by <a href="https://hamel.dev/">Hamel Husain</a>.</p>
<p>I have seen chatbots, yet the way ChatGPT interacts and communicates is insane to be honest. You can ask it literally anything and these Large Language models are becoming incredibly useful. Hamel had used <a href="https://github.com/hwchase17/langchain/">LangChain</a> which is like a framework for building applications with LLMs specifically for quarto.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://www.gsb.stanford.edu/sites/default/files/styles/1630x_variable_tinypng/public/resources/ng-ai-1630_1.jpg.webp?itok=9_DYUOPs" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>An Image from gsb.stanford.edu article on Andrew NG remark</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</section>
<section id="how-has-the-ai-landscape-been-going-in-the-past-one-year" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="how-has-the-ai-landscape-been-going-in-the-past-one-year">How has the AI landscape been going in the past one year?</h2>
<p>Personally I have been following ML/AI for the past five years atleast. Last year really was hyped up. Initially there was this releases in DALL-E and it’s open source alternative Craiyon(then named DALLE mini) being viral. During this time so many trending things like Stable Diffusion, Whisper etc came.</p>
<p>One month back, I started seeing my cousins, parents etc. discussing about ChatGPT and how awesome it is. Some of the application apps like <a href="https://www.roamaround.io">Roamaround.ai</a> build on top of ChatGPT was being used. The final nail was last Sunday, when my grandfather called me to read about ChatGPT article in news.</p>
<p>I have seen people get hyped up about advances in ML. Yet I have never heard about the new technology being discussed by any of my family member like this. Hamel Hussein put this really well in his tweet about what is different in this wave of ML advances.</p>
<p></p><div id="tweet-97364"></div><script>tweet={"url":"https:\/\/twitter.com\/HamelHusain\/status\/1636513242041442305","author_name":"Hamel Husain","author_url":"https:\/\/twitter.com\/HamelHusain","html":"\u003Cblockquote class=\"twitter-tweet\" align=\"center\"\u003E\u003Cp lang=\"en\" dir=\"ltr\"\u003EThis wave of ML advances feels different than all others before it.  Usually, lots of people sleep on it or just pay lip service to ML.  \u003Cbr\u003E\u003Cbr\u003EThis time, people are rushing to ship ML products, and successfully doing so at breakneck speed.\u003C\/p\u003E&mdash; Hamel Husain (@HamelHusain) \u003Ca href=\"https:\/\/twitter.com\/HamelHusain\/status\/1636513242041442305?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw\"\u003EMarch 16, 2023\u003C\/a\u003E\u003C\/blockquote\u003E\n\u003Cscript async src=\"https:\/\/platform.twitter.com\/widgets.js\" charset=\"utf-8\"\u003E\u003C\/script\u003E\n\n","width":550,"height":null,"type":"rich","cache_age":"3153600000","provider_name":"Twitter","provider_url":"https:\/\/twitter.com","version":"1.0"};document.getElementById("tweet-97364").innerHTML = tweet["html"];</script><p></p>
</section>
<section id="release-of-gpt-4" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="release-of-gpt-4">Release of GPT-4</h2>
<p>The GPT-4 model was released by OpenAI today IST. It’s been a hectic week already TBH, with so many releases already.</p>
<p></p><div id="tweet-69415"></div><script>tweet={"url":"https:\/\/twitter.com\/iScienceLuvr\/status\/1635747429839671300","author_name":"Tanishq Mathew Abraham, Ph.D.","author_url":"https:\/\/twitter.com\/iScienceLuvr","html":"\u003Cblockquote class=\"twitter-tweet\" align=\"center\"\u003E\u003Cp lang=\"ro\" dir=\"ltr\"\u003EGPT-4 release\u003Cbr\u003EMed-PaLM2 announcement\u003Cbr\u003EPaLM API release\u003Cbr\u003EClaude API release \u003Ca href=\"https:\/\/t.co\/Oef6qw6uhf\"\u003Epic.twitter.com\/Oef6qw6uhf\u003C\/a\u003E\u003C\/p\u003E&mdash; Tanishq Mathew Abraham, Ph.D. (@iScienceLuvr) \u003Ca href=\"https:\/\/twitter.com\/iScienceLuvr\/status\/1635747429839671300?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw\"\u003EMarch 14, 2023\u003C\/a\u003E\u003C\/blockquote\u003E\n\u003Cscript async src=\"https:\/\/platform.twitter.com\/widgets.js\" charset=\"utf-8\"\u003E\u003C\/script\u003E\n\n","width":550,"height":null,"type":"rich","cache_age":"3153600000","provider_name":"Twitter","provider_url":"https:\/\/twitter.com","version":"1.0"};document.getElementById("tweet-69415").innerHTML = tweet["html"];</script><p></p>
<p>The initial reaction to this model has been awesome, and lot of people have been reacting about this.</p>
<p></p><div id="tweet-10481"></div><script>tweet={"url":"https:\/\/twitter.com\/Suhail\/status\/1635704809725767680","author_name":"Suhail","author_url":"https:\/\/twitter.com\/Suhail","html":"\u003Cblockquote class=\"twitter-tweet\" align=\"center\"\u003E\u003Cp lang=\"en\" dir=\"ltr\"\u003EWe tried GPT-4 internally over the past few months and it is *a lot* better than meets the eye. I encourage folks to try it. World changing technology.\u003C\/p\u003E&mdash; Suhail (@Suhail) \u003Ca href=\"https:\/\/twitter.com\/Suhail\/status\/1635704809725767680?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw\"\u003EMarch 14, 2023\u003C\/a\u003E\u003C\/blockquote\u003E\n\u003Cscript async src=\"https:\/\/platform.twitter.com\/widgets.js\" charset=\"utf-8\"\u003E\u003C\/script\u003E\n\n","width":550,"height":null,"type":"rich","cache_age":"3153600000","provider_name":"Twitter","provider_url":"https:\/\/twitter.com","version":"1.0"};document.getElementById("tweet-10481").innerHTML = tweet["html"];</script><p></p>
<p>You can read more about this release in below resources:</p>
<p><a href="https://openai.com/research/gpt-4">Research document</a></p>
<p><a href="https://openai.com/product/gpt-4">Product details</a></p>
<p>Check out the summary of what was highlights of GPT-4 and it’s developer livestream in this tweet thread by FSDL.</p>
<p></p><div id="tweet-14151"></div><script>tweet={"url":"https:\/\/twitter.com\/full_stack_dl\/status\/1635734384463745024","author_name":"The Full Stack","author_url":"https:\/\/twitter.com\/full_stack_dl","html":"\u003Cblockquote class=\"twitter-tweet\" align=\"center\"\u003E\u003Cp lang=\"en\" dir=\"ltr\"\u003ELive-tweeting the GPT-4 livestream from OpenAI ⤵️\u003C\/p\u003E&mdash; The Full Stack (@full_stack_dl) \u003Ca href=\"https:\/\/twitter.com\/full_stack_dl\/status\/1635734384463745024?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw\"\u003EMarch 14, 2023\u003C\/a\u003E\u003C\/blockquote\u003E\n\u003Cscript async src=\"https:\/\/platform.twitter.com\/widgets.js\" charset=\"utf-8\"\u003E\u003C\/script\u003E\n\n","width":550,"height":null,"type":"rich","cache_age":"3153600000","provider_name":"Twitter","provider_url":"https:\/\/twitter.com","version":"1.0"};document.getElementById("tweet-14151").innerHTML = tweet["html"];</script><p></p>
</section>
<section id="how-can-we-try-gpt-4-now" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="how-can-we-try-gpt-4-now">How can we try GPT-4 now?</h2>
<p>According to OpenAI, you can try the latest GPT-4 via Chat GPT Plus Membership.</p>
<p>Two more options seems to be available for normal users without mulimodal search:</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>BingGPT</li>
<li>Poe App from Quora</li>
</ol>
</section>
<section id="is-binggpt-really-using-gpt-4" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="is-binggpt-really-using-gpt-4">Is BingGPT really using GPT-4?</h2>
<p>To be honest, at the moment we can’t be really sure about that. Even though as Microsoft <a href="https://blogs.bing.com/search/march_2023/Confirmed-the-new-Bing-runs-on-OpenAI%E2%80%99s-GPT-4">Bing team confirmed today that they are using GPT-4</a>.</p>
<p>In lot of user tests, it doesn’t really seem to be the same. I tested a trick question:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>Which is heavier, two pounds of brick or one pound of feathers?</p>
</blockquote>
<p>GPT-4 seems to give the correct answer at time of writing.</p>
<p></p><div id="tweet-68202"></div><script>tweet={"url":"https:\/\/twitter.com\/charles_irl\/status\/1635699547023482880","author_name":"Charles \uD83C\uDF89 Frye","author_url":"https:\/\/twitter.com\/charles_irl","html":"\u003Cblockquote class=\"twitter-tweet\" align=\"center\"\u003E\u003Cp lang=\"en\" dir=\"ltr\"\u003Egpt-4 passes the &quot;two pounds of bricks&quot; adversarial question without prompt fiddling \u003Ca href=\"https:\/\/t.co\/jRcYzxSr38\"\u003Epic.twitter.com\/jRcYzxSr38\u003C\/a\u003E\u003C\/p\u003E&mdash; Charles \uD83C\uDF89 Frye (@charles_irl) \u003Ca href=\"https:\/\/twitter.com\/charles_irl\/status\/1635699547023482880?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw\"\u003EMarch 14, 2023\u003C\/a\u003E\u003C\/blockquote\u003E\n\u003Cscript async src=\"https:\/\/platform.twitter.com\/widgets.js\" charset=\"utf-8\"\u003E\u003C\/script\u003E\n\n","width":550,"height":null,"type":"rich","cache_age":"3153600000","provider_name":"Twitter","provider_url":"https:\/\/twitter.com","version":"1.0"};document.getElementById("tweet-68202").innerHTML = tweet["html"];</script><p></p>
<p>Bing-GPT seems to give wrong answer.</p>
<p></p><div id="tweet-61468"></div><script>tweet={"url":"https:\/\/twitter.com\/kurianbenoy2\/status\/1636066002843627523","author_name":"Kurian Benoy \uD83D\uDCBB","author_url":"https:\/\/twitter.com\/kurianbenoy2","html":"\u003Cblockquote class=\"twitter-tweet\" align=\"center\"\u003E\u003Cp lang=\"en\" dir=\"ltr\"\u003EIs it really GPT-4 though? \u003Ca href=\"https:\/\/t.co\/UZXvapfM6k\"\u003Epic.twitter.com\/UZXvapfM6k\u003C\/a\u003E\u003C\/p\u003E&mdash; Kurian Benoy \uD83D\uDCBB (@kurianbenoy2) \u003Ca href=\"https:\/\/twitter.com\/kurianbenoy2\/status\/1636066002843627523?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw\"\u003EMarch 15, 2023\u003C\/a\u003E\u003C\/blockquote\u003E\n\u003Cscript async src=\"https:\/\/platform.twitter.com\/widgets.js\" charset=\"utf-8\"\u003E\u003C\/script\u003E\n\n","width":550,"height":null,"type":"rich","cache_age":"3153600000","provider_name":"Twitter","provider_url":"https:\/\/twitter.com","version":"1.0"};document.getElementById("tweet-61468").innerHTML = tweet["html"];</script><p></p>
<p>Chat-GPT seems to now give correct answer, it was previously giving wrong answer.</p>
<p></p><div id="tweet-38775"></div><script>tweet={"url":"https:\/\/twitter.com\/1littlecoder\/status\/1636069386699022336","author_name":"1LittleCoder\uD83D\uDCBB","author_url":"https:\/\/twitter.com\/1littlecoder","html":"\u003Cblockquote class=\"twitter-tweet\" align=\"center\"\u003E\u003Cp lang=\"en\" dir=\"ltr\"\u003EOlder ChatGPt corrected \u003Ca href=\"https:\/\/t.co\/RNXgq5bL8K\"\u003Epic.twitter.com\/RNXgq5bL8K\u003C\/a\u003E\u003C\/p\u003E&mdash; 1LittleCoder\uD83D\uDCBB (@1littlecoder) \u003Ca href=\"https:\/\/twitter.com\/1littlecoder\/status\/1636069386699022336?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw\"\u003EMarch 15, 2023\u003C\/a\u003E\u003C\/blockquote\u003E\n\u003Cscript async src=\"https:\/\/platform.twitter.com\/widgets.js\" charset=\"utf-8\"\u003E\u003C\/script\u003E\n\n","width":550,"height":null,"type":"rich","cache_age":"3153600000","provider_name":"Twitter","provider_url":"https:\/\/twitter.com","version":"1.0"};document.getElementById("tweet-38775").innerHTML = tweet["html"];</script><p></p>
<p>Charles seems to have come with an explaination to this problem, at the time I was writing this article.</p>
<p><em>“GPT-4” is really a series of models, and the one live in chat now is likely the 0314 checkpoint available via the API. BingChat can’t’ve launched with that checkpoint and likely has branched off in the intervening weeks.”</em></p>
<p></p><div id="tweet-26246"></div><script>tweet={"url":"https:\/\/twitter.com\/charles_irl\/status\/1636071852593549312","author_name":"Charles \uD83C\uDF89 Frye","author_url":"https:\/\/twitter.com\/charles_irl","html":"\u003Cblockquote class=\"twitter-tweet\" align=\"center\"\u003E\u003Cp lang=\"en\" dir=\"ltr\"\u003ENice find! &quot;GPT-4&quot; is really a series of models, and the one live in chat now is likely the 0314 checkpoint available via the API. BingChat can&#39;t&#39;ve launched with that checkpoint and likely has branched off in the intervening weeks.\u003C\/p\u003E&mdash; Charles \uD83C\uDF89 Frye (@charles_irl) \u003Ca href=\"https:\/\/twitter.com\/charles_irl\/status\/1636071852593549312?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw\"\u003EMarch 15, 2023\u003C\/a\u003E\u003C\/blockquote\u003E\n\u003Cscript async src=\"https:\/\/platform.twitter.com\/widgets.js\" charset=\"utf-8\"\u003E\u003C\/script\u003E\n\n","width":550,"height":null,"type":"rich","cache_age":"3153600000","provider_name":"Twitter","provider_url":"https:\/\/twitter.com","version":"1.0"};document.getElementById("tweet-26246").innerHTML = tweet["html"];</script><p></p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>Deep learning</category>
  <category>NLP</category>
  <category>coding</category>
  <guid>https://kurianbenoy.com/posts/2023/gpt4/</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 15 Mar 2023 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>My daily fitness routine</title>
  <dc:creator>Kurian Benoy</dc:creator>
  <link>https://kurianbenoy.com/posts/2023/fitness_journey/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://user-images.githubusercontent.com/24592806/223161083-1a5cfc9b-03f0-4425-a1d6-ebc398542727.png" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>Stable diffusion image generated with prompt Very muscular man, photograph quality, ultra detailed</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Hello everyone, I just thought of sharing my daily fitness routine which I have been following for the past 1 month. Previously I had written about <a href="https://kurianbenoy.com/posts/2020/2020-11-22-weightloss.html">How I lost almost 4Kgs in 3 weeks - my wegiht loss Journey</a>. I want to continue this journey, even though just after writing that post I gained a lot of kilos and I couldn’t follow everything I mentioned in that article.</p>
<p>So this time, I am with a new routine:</p>
<p>During morning I go to gym and do High Intensity Interval Training (HIIT) for 30-45 minutes. In the gym I go, this usually consists of 8 stations of 3 minutes exercises followed by 30 seconds rest. The first four stations are vary day after day, followed by a challenge which changes every week. After this I do boxing, followed by two more stations of 3 minutes exercises which usually are floor exercises.</p>
<p>In evening I go for a walk for 45-60 minutes after my work. I usually try to walk almost 4 kilometers and monitor my progress in Strava app. I usually walk in the roads near my home till a paddy field and then return back. My usual pace is 4.5-6 km/h and I cover one kilometer in approximately 11-12 minutes.</p>
<p>Some of you might be wondering why I am sharing this, well I am sharing this as I want to document my fitness progress. Looking back, I myself can look at things I did and see how I progressed. I also want to share this with others who are interested.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>myself</category>
  <guid>https://kurianbenoy.com/posts/2023/fitness_journey/</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 06 Mar 2023 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Attending MBIFL 2023, a literature festival</title>
  <dc:creator>Kurian Benoy</dc:creator>
  <link>https://kurianbenoy.com/posts/2023/mbifl2023/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>Since I am a frequent book purchaser from Mathrubhumi book, in January I got a notification to buy early bird tickets for <a href="https://www.mbifl.com/speakers-2023/">MBIFL 2023</a>. I immediately bought 4 day’s tickets to attend the literature festival. When it came to February, I realised due to some commitments at home and work, I couldn’t attend all the days of this literature festival despite having a ticket.</p>
<p>MBIFL had almost 300+ speakers, with famous speakers like Nobel prize winners, Brooker prize winners, politicians etc.</p>
<p>Yet I had just one wish. <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Benyamin_(writer)">Benyamin</a> is an author who has written lot of thriller novels like അൽ - അറേബ്യൻ നോവൽ ഫാക്‌ടറി and മുല്ലപ്പു നിറമുള്ള പകലുകൾ(which is a dual novel) along with the famous ആടു ജീവിതം(Goat Days). I just wanted to meet him in person and get an autograph on my copy of my favourite novel.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-left">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://kurianbenoy.com/posts/2023/mbifl2023/book.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" width="300"></p>
<figcaption>My favourite novel</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>I travelled early morning from my house and reached the venue by almost 10:30 AM. During this time, there was a conversational session about പ്രവാസിയുടെ അക്ഷരകാലം with P Sreeramkrishan, Benyamin, Shabini Vasudev and KV Mohan Kumar. After the session, there was a huge fan base to meet author Benyamin. I first went to get a signature from another author KV Mohan Kumar in the panel, and then waited in the queue to get a signature from Benyamin.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-left">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://kurianbenoy.com/posts/2023/mbifl2023/benyamin_session.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" width="300"></p>
<figcaption>Session on പ്രവാസിയുടെ അക്ഷരകാലം</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>After lot of books were signed by Benyamin which was bought by his fans with some of his famous works like ആടു ജീവിതം, മാന്തളിരിലെ ഇരുപത് കമ്മ്യൂണിസ്ററ് വർഷങ്ങൾ, അൽ - അറേബ്യൻ നോവൽ ഫാക്‌ടറി. I got my copy also signed with a salutation of snehattode(with love). I just asked my favourite author does a person named Sameera Parveen who was a character in Jasmine Days really exist or not. Benyam answered that it’s a mixture of multiple people who he had seen in his life, yet there is no one such person who doesn’t exist as Sameera Parveen like Najeeb in ആടു ജീവിതം.</p>
<p>My mission was just completed in one hour and I got a few more signatures like Shabini Vasudev who is an author from Bahrain and from Vinu V John, who is the star anchor of Asianet news(who kindly reminded me he is not famous to be giving autograph).</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-left">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://kurianbenoy.com/posts/2023/mbifl2023/book_signature.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" width="300"></p>
<figcaption>All the signature I got</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>After that, I attended the talk with Aparna Balamurali and Captian GR Gopinath. Shashi Tharoor talked about his book Pride, Prejudice and Punditry. Seeing Tharoor answer a question to a student reminded me of India’s former people’s president APJ. I wish him all the success as a politician.</p>
<p>One of the last sessions I attended that day was by Polish author Justi Guziak on Know yourself to express yourself. This session talked about improvising and was a hands-on workshop to learn this art. During the session, the speakers gave me a chit with the question <code>what was the best gift you have ever received?</code>. This question was to be asked to someone who was at the other end of the audience. I gave my question and Janaki who was from Thiruvananthapuram told me the best gift she ever received was a dog she received when she was in her 7th standard. This dog has been living with her for the past 15 years as a constant when she went through her school, then college and even after her marriage. Another situation which was given during the workshop was to convince Mr Karun to give something valuable in his hand. After a lot of convincing, I was able to share the lunch with Karun.</p>
<p>That winded up MBIFL 2023, a literature festival for me a data scientist who doesn’t have anything related to it. It was cool to interact and meet with so many cool people. I am looking forward to MBIFL 2024 soon…</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-left">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://kurianbenoy.com/posts/2023/mbifl2023/tharoor.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" width="500"></p>
<figcaption>Session by Shashi Tharoor</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p><em>Update 1(March 5, 2023)</em></p>
<p>I found a very cool video in 360 degree which showed how the MBIFL 2023 venue atmosphere is. It was a very cool video and I thought of including this also with this blogpost.</p>
<div class="quarto-video ratio ratio-16x9"><iframe data-external="1" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/ZrbFzIFu-d0" title="" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen=""></iframe></div>



 ]]></description>
  <category>Life</category>
  <category>Travel</category>
  <category>conference</category>
  <guid>https://kurianbenoy.com/posts/2023/mbifl2023/</guid>
  <pubDate>Sun, 05 Feb 2023 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Welcome To My Quarto Website</title>
  <dc:creator>Tristan O&#39;Malley</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Kurian Benoy</dc:creator>
  <link>https://kurianbenoy.com/posts/2023/welcome/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p><img src="https://kurianbenoy.com/posts/2023/welcome/thumbnail.jpg" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>This is my first post in a Quarto blog. Welcome everyone to my new blog.</p>
<p>I have been wanting for a long time to unify <a href="https://github.com/kurianbenoy/ml-blog">my existing Machine learning blog</a> based on fast-pages together with <a href="https://github.com/kurianbenoy/kurianbenoy.github.io/tree/4b5246ada3190dbdd73dc96d266a5ade7ef078a3">my main blog website</a>.</p>
<p>The unification process is a bit challenging:</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>All my previous blog post in main website was written with <a href="https://github.com/daattali/beautiful-jekyll">beautiful jekyll</a> format using markdown.</li>
<li>Need support for jupyter-notebook, which beautiful jekyll doesn’t support</li>
</ol>
<p>This is where Quarto comes as a saviour. It has wide support for various formats like markdown, jupyter notebook, rmarkdown. The goal, JJ and team is looking to have a single source of publication is really interesting. I was already familiar with nbdev with few of the projects I previously made.</p>
<p>I converted all of my existing blog post in markdown to fastpages markdown format. Then I leveraged <a href="https://nbdev.fast.ai/migrating.html">nbdev 1 migration scripts</a> to move it to quarto.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>TIL</category>
  <category>coding</category>
  <category>Webdev</category>
  <guid>https://kurianbenoy.com/posts/2023/welcome/</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 16 Jan 2023 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
